[SPEAKER_01]: I was just thinking about that, eh, ordination and certificates from institutions, you know, regarding ordination, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something you need.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need divine rights to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need authority to give you those rights, those certificates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it wasn't like that in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, mind you, the ordination and the whole thing we go through, that did come from the Buddha, it evolved in that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a valid thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I know what you mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of the other kind of politics involved with the saṅgha in the West, in Thailand, in Sri Lanka, all of the all of the polities that now exist and so on, that all came later.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, and the, and anyway, there's nothing to do with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yes, in the early days, remember when the Buddha was just walking around and had all of it, he would be, oh, wow, that dhamma seems really true, can I follow you?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, yes, come here, bhikkhu.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would address him bhikkhu, and that would mean he's now part of the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all it took.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because back then, well, it was all about the dhamma, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: That was the bond, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was clear what the dhamma was, it was clear what the practice was, so people knew it straight and there would be enough for them to join and make the effort and become arahants.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, obviously, in a course of time, over the years, things were getting a bit more complicated.
[SPEAKER_00]: The rules were being made because the monks were breaking, doing unwholesome stuff and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it evolved to the point, okay, now you need a senior monk, you need at least ten other bhikkhus present, and then you can have upasampada, ordination, and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's all, again, that's all still relatively simple.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's also... and that's an issue as well, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you think, right now, now, I'm sort of safe, I am practicing now... Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was going to say that the reason why it actually evolved
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, proliferate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a form of involvement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Proliferate more than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now, people don't have the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: They might find it on the individual level, through their individual efforts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, when you come to any order, be Theravāda, Zen, whatever, on an average level, what you hear being taught, it's nothing to... it's very little... well, it's not dhamma, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might be talking about the dhamma, but listening to it, you won't become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You... even if you make the effort upon it, it's basically wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because of that, means there is no that kind of clear seeing of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Buddha meant when he said the dhamma will die 500 years after his passing away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean it will be impossible to become an arahant later.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means that when it's being spoken, when it's being referred to, when it's being quoted, it's most likely going to be wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, it's going to refer to the wrong thing as the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it won't be the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, as I said, a person can dig through that and find it on an individual level, but not on the level of community, society, religion, teachers, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for that very reason, people, exactly, they need this form of belonging.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they need something more significant to make them feel...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, to feel a certain bond with whatever they want to do with this life, so with the holy life, with the order they're joining.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you... if somebody just comes off the street and you say, okay, come here, Bhikkhu, here is the door, he most likely won't take it serious.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter how much he wants.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, well, his personal attitude, his personal reasons for practice are not clear to himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: If, on the other hand, a fully self-transparent, authentic person, puthujjana, comes off the street, there will be enough of him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he knows the place of it, he knows what he's supposed to do, he knows why he is here for.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he won't ever need that external, artificial, superficial sense of, I belong to something bigger, or these robes, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes can help to people in the beginning, but it's not really essential, because if they don't start clearing up the bad faith internally, they'll never
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they never really made the proper effort, which means they never really discovered dharma, which means they will never ever be the valid, the right type of connection with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will all be maintained by the external circumstances, such as the robes, the rules, the community you live in, they will keep you together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the practice of the wisdom that you develop, because Arahant, he doesn't have to.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he will, because that's the lifestyle that corresponds the best to Arahantship, which is why he would have created it in such ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's a... it's a... if you were to actually only pick up, like, for example, monks who ordained
[SPEAKER_00]: Clear reasons, without bad faith, relatively authentic.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't find many.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't find many, which means that most of the people rely on the external form to keep them together.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is a form of sīlabata paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't see the place of the rules.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think the virtue is the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think keeping your rules together is the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the practice is, but it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a prerequisite.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's something that needs to be in place, but it's not the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as I said to you probably in the past as well, so you have to find out how can you not keep the rules without breaking them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because breaking the rules, again, that's against the practice, for sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, holding the rules is also against the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you not break the rules, but then not be... not... not keep them either?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you let go of syllabus, but must let go, or rather put it in the right place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you guys... you guys, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Eight precepts, the basic, the fundamentals of Ayurveda, you know, basic precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else, you know, celibacy, part of it, but everything else is something very necessary, old.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eight precepts are the kind of core of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I would always refer to.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you would be talking about the olden times, the wise men of the past, it would always be around the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be the symbol of virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: And morality established, that can lead to wisdom, if a person makes the right effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the rest is just community growing?
[SPEAKER_00]: The rest of it, as he said himself, on his deathbed, it was utterly circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, you can do away with most of the rules, smaller rules, that I've made.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were just a response to a recent problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, Ananda forgot to ask what those rules were, so then the Arhat said, well, let's just keep them, because people will, and they would have criticized right away, saying, ah, look, the teacher died, and now they abolished half of the rules.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The order is done.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a, you know...
[SPEAKER_01]: But maybe the way you said it now, maybe you said it in a similar way, like, oh, you could actually
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, it could have been like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, yes, I see what you mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, it's not because there were... the rules were kind of in different
[SPEAKER_00]: They make no difference to the practice of the dhamma, whether you practice or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just makes no difference to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, having them or not, most of those smaller rules we talked about, having them or not, doesn't make a difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, making a big point out of a portion and really finding out, it's... well, it's a waste of time and most likely, it might be coming out of something unwholesome, if somebody's so keen to get rid of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: revolution.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm gonna make a new order or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's silly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's a waste of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's worrying.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yes, in the beginning, there were no rules.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, there was one rule.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, there were two rules.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, there were three rules.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how it evolved.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is, you know, the famous story of that monk who came and said, oh, I just...
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to disrobe.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not, she said, I'm not, I'm not unhappy with the dhamma or anything like that, but there are way too many rules and I cannot possibly keep...
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, I can't keep all 147 rules, which was funny, because now we have 227.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, which means, when this monk was complaining, not all of them were yet created.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he said, it's just too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I can't possibly keep that in my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: I won't, you know, I don't want to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And everybody says, okay, well, can you keep three rules then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't do anything unwholesome by body, by speech, or mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, I think, there might be another story.
[SPEAKER_00]: In this case, he just said... he said... Can you just... No, I think that came from Ajahn Chah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just watch your mind, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, this was like, don't do anything unwholesome by body, by speech, or by mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you do that?
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, yeah, of course, that's easy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, because he knew what Dharma also was, but he couldn't be bothered about the specifics.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is how you wear your robe.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is how you put your sitting cloth.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're breaking the rule.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is ridiculous, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that man had a point, and the Buddha knew that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he said, well, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fair enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people can see it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can you keep the three rules?
[SPEAKER_00]: And do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what refers to, like in the suttas, abhidhamma and abhivinna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It refers to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just more, well, more detailed, higher, in a sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You surmount it, you come to the core.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point of every rule is not to do anything unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, if you're focused on not doing anything unwholesome, automatically, you cannot break the rule.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if, actually, externally, you're putting your sitting cloth wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not breaking the rule in that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's breaking the circumstantial irrelevant rule, for which you might be told off, and for which you won't feel anything, because, you know, it doesn't pertain to anything of significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why you won't have a problem keeping it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't make a difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: If some of these people get too wound up, you might not want to... you might want to make a point to them, that it's their mistake, but that's more related to ridiculous koans and stuff that comes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It comes with the communities.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when it comes to rules, it works like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know what's important and you know there is no compromise there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, the other rules are just kind of involved in a form of a response to the recent situations for the duration of the Buddha's lifetime, while he was around.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, technically and theoretically,
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have to keep the eight precepts strictly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The stricter you keep them, the... well, the sharper you are, the more precise you can get.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, you know, if sometimes people are like, oh, too much, like, oh, there's this little rule and that little rule and...
[SPEAKER_00]: I must not do this, and I can't move the soil, but I can move the soil if it's been disturbed, or it's been at least four weeks before, or three months, or too much... well, the rain has the... it's just... it is too complicated, and it's utterly non-essential.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if on the other hand, we focus on the eight precepts, and you really keep an eye on them, so not even by mind that you're engaging in breaking them, in terms of the unwholesome thought, then even if you go and you take the ground,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Externally, it's an offense, and you should confess it, and somebody will tell you off.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you know you're breaking that rule, so to speak, you won't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know it's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you know that if you don't do it, there is even no... there's zero ground to be harassed, to be hassled by somebody telling you off, or, like, shouldn't be doing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's utterly irrelevant whether you do it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is that element of, oh, well, other people don't know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they will most likely hassle me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I don't...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't want to be hassled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would I be hassled?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: I need to deal with other people's issues.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you just don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it seems like, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But we don't get hassled, yeah, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, seriously, I think a lot of people choose just to be self-aware.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't actually... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't really...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's their reasons, maybe, to be...
[SPEAKER_00]: It often actually is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, the few people I've met that have been monks, and there were samaneras, and then monks, and then samaneras, it was usually revolving around that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just, they felt it was too restrictive, for no significant reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can see their point, because it's not just that it's too restrictive from the vinaya point of view, but it's too restrictive from the cultural point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kovat point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, in Sri Lanka, they might not have so much emphasis on kovar as they do in the West or Thailand, but certainly, it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are things, oh, no, that's not proper.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all... it's... it's often relatively random, depending on what... what monk tell... what monk tells you there is some proper... that's improper or not, but it's still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, you shouldn't be holding the broom like that, or... What?
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all of that can actually wind people up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... if somebody's serious with their practice, then, yeah, it doesn't make a difference whether you're a samanera or a bhikkhu.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it doesn't make a difference even if you're a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the way, it's much harder as a layman because wearing the robe is also a form of statement for others.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, it implies a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: It tells others what you are, so you don't have to explain.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you just turn up as a layman in a group of laypeople, they'll think you're a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might be anāgāmī in your mind, but they think you're a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they'll treat you like that, they'll expose you to lay things, they'll hassle you with lay things, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a monk, they won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, if they do, they will at least know that you're not a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, they might choose to ignore that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it is a formal statement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, by wearing the robe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which was also the time in India.
[SPEAKER_00]: They could have... and then, yeah, some of them just went off.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, they would put on any robes and they would immediately stand up.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's a sādhu, he's a religious person, he's the seeker of the spiritual life.
[SPEAKER_00]: They often wouldn't know what kind of seeker, what kind, and then they would go, oh, who's your teacher?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, what teaching do you follow?
[SPEAKER_00]: They wouldn't have a clue, because you couldn't tell.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're all wrapped in rags and robes and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it can be anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, the thing is like this, as you say now, you're subject to other people's... Expectations, yeah, hassle, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people stop short when there's a road, and you walk on the corner, people take their hats off, kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep quiet, move aside, something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, if you live in an environment that still includes your friends or your family or stuff like that,
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, if you're a layperson, you have to go and hide on top of the mountain, because otherwise, you know, people would demand things from you, would need things from you, would require.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's still possible, as it was possible in the Buddha's day.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be technically an anāgāmī as a layperson, but it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's unbelievably hard.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's hard to become an anāgāmī as a monk, let alone as a person, layperson out there in the world, today.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, it was hard back in India as well, but I guess that their lives were a bit less proliferated than ours.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there were less distraction, less pressure, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the minds were also a bit less proliferative.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh, the point is... Where is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Go on.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was thinking, what's the most important thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Authenticity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's the...
[SPEAKER_01]: The number one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being authentic, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But being authentic, as it's in...
[SPEAKER_01]: I would say, you know, that's a very plain thing, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, if you just... as I would say, authentic, you know, it is quite plain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But how do you know that you aren't being authentic?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, there is no... like...
[SPEAKER_00]: Checkpoint that lights up as you pass the level, a sufficient degree of authenticity.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, a little beep, letting you know, okay, you're in the clear now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take your mask off.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's not like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know it by...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, but various things, and I think it varies from... like, different people would recognize it when I call it different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, first of all, it's very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, authenticity in itself will not lead you to peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: Becoming authentic, what it does, it removes all of the unwholesome ways that you have built up in the course of your life,
[SPEAKER_00]: to manage or to obscure the fact that you're suffering, that existence is unpleasant, that existence is not yours, that it's dreadful, that it's terrifying.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you use acts of bad faith to cover that up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you know, you can you can feel at ease, you can feel confident, whatever else, whatever habits you've built.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, authenticity undoes all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it really exposes you back to just pure, well, of dread, anxiety, because your entire being as a whole, everything, your sense of self, you start to feel it's just completely exposed, anything, and you have no control over it, yet you don't know how to stop holding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's quite a dreadful situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what authenticity does.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like all of the... the existential philosophers that did talk about it, preach it, practice it themselves, could not quite sustain it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kierkegaard, apparently, you know, he was... apparently, on his deathbed, he said he never had a moment of peace in his life, from the moment he decided he'd become a philosopher.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he meant that in a right sense, not kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: theoretical, pondering, Hegelian type, but more like genuinely living what he's thinking, what he's preaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he was considered one of the first existentialists for those reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he really made an attitude out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He broke off his engagement, left the woman that he was really in love with and didn't want to accept the world position in some... because that would just made him like... well, it would kind of settle him and it would
[SPEAKER_00]: Providing an illusion of existential safety, which he knew was not right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although, every ounce of his being wanted to accept it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because everybody gives in to the offers of safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how it works.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he refused.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, he was putridian, so he didn't know the way out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but he would refuse to give in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, basically, that for the rest of his life, he was on a... well,
[SPEAKER_00]: On a verge of a breakdown, constantly, with, you know, facing the existential anxiety and everything else, yet not giving in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he will be writing, like, two or three 500 pages book... 500 pages books per year, publishing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just look at the publishing 14, 15, 6 every year.
[SPEAKER_00]: Massive volumes of work, because it was just so intense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Nietzsche as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, Nietzsche lost it in the end.
[SPEAKER_00]: He kind of... he pushed it so far, refused to give in, and went mad as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, the Buddha did say that if a person correctly, genuinely, authentically starts experiencing suffering, recognizes the nature of suffering, there are two outcomes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Noble search or mental derangement.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Nietzsche, by refusing the Christian God, went mad, because he really left no footing for him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kierkegaard refused to let go of the idea of the Eternal God and Savior, which made him really, like, funny.
[SPEAKER_00]: You read this really acute existential description, and then just switches into this God preaching weird
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely discrepant stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contradictory.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he refused.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what actually, I think, kept him sane.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because without having that little bad faith, he would have fully exposed himself to the nature of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And without the Buddha's help, you cannot... you'd go mad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you'll immediately, you know, commit to the dhamma if you've known there is such a thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's what authenticity does for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's just inconceivable to succeed in any way in the dhamma without that as a starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because for as long as you're entertaining and holding on to the views and beliefs that you have built up as a result of covering up the nature of existence in the course of your lifetime, you cannot possibly then start applying right view and right things onto it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're holding on to the wrong things and wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a form of safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, like, you know, people can... many people, many monks can know for a fact, openly, they're not even a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't know escape from something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, which means they refuse to let go of things they're keeping in puthujjana, but at the same time offering them sense of safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, at the same time, they can believe that they are practicing the dhamma, and they're able to teach and preach about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's utter contradiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't know the way yourself, you can't teach the way yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't know the way yourself, because you're refusing to let go of the wrong ways that you have accumulated as a form of... as a form of a buffer zone, as a protection.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the first thing you will notice, by practicing... by becoming authentic, is complete... dissolvement, so to speak, of your confidence.
[SPEAKER_00]: The confidence that you built as a as a layperson just completely disappears in regard to everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You feel utterly exposed in every way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, gradually, if you again don't go mad, don't do anything stupid, don't give up,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the right view can emerge from that, because you're not obstructing it by any holding that is there to delude you, to cover things up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not doing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're refusing to engage in an act of ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, avijjā is being... not being maintained.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't... you still don't know that, but that's the... that's how your experience is being set up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, by thinking about dhamma practice and dhamma, then you actually start to recognize things that the Buddha was talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is what a vijaya is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a metaphysical veil of delusion, maya, or whatever else, depending on the religion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not something that is, you know, to be found, to be discovered in an instant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, turn the stone, it's right there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Finally, you found it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was hidden.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the very act.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the very attitude of your mind, day in, day out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bad faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring, actively not looking at certain things, actively not acknowledging those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, technically speaking, anybody is even vaguely familiar with the suttas, has a vague idea of the dhamma, if he was to start practicing authenticity, he will naturally go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, even that vague instruction that he came across, might be quite sufficient.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more authentic you are, less instruction you need.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more authentic you are, you understand whatever comes up, doesn't... if it's inauthentic, it doesn't stand up for too long.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it doesn't maintain itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think through.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, like, as the suttas say, that the aggregates, the five aggregates, are being taken up by your assumption, by upādāna, in the same way a fire takes up the fuel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the fire burns the fuel, takes this up to be the fuel.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the fuel maintains the fire in return.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the fire, through burning the fuel, spreads over that fuel and keeps burning.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the same sense, upādāna, an assumption, through maintaining, it may... through engaging in it, it's maintaining itself in regard to your experience as a whole, which is what the five aggregates are.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, authentic person might be a patujana, he doesn't know the dhamma, but if he recognizes
[SPEAKER_00]: The validity, the wholesomeness of being authentic, and he starts doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't know yet, but what he's doing, he's not actually engaging anymore in ignoring, so he's not maintaining his avijjā, he's not maintaining his upādāna, he's not maintaining his craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's exposing it all and not engaging in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can't a person be, like, missing or think, knowing that they are doing something which is based on lust, based on anger?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And know it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that's craving, that's craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: But can't you do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, you can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, well, I mean, they can, but that's not offending.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're authentic initially on the level of recognition, but they're not authentic on the level of engaging physically in those unwholesome acts, or mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, like, as I said, the fact you recognize this is unwholesome, but then you choose to give in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you abandon your authenticity right there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, thinking you're authentic while you're engaging in inauthentic acts is a contradiction in terms, which means you're inauthentic.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, when you think of yourself as authentic, you're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you just gave in.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yes, as I said, a person can undo a lot of unwholesome things, which are things that maintain avidya, maintain craving, perpetuate craving and so on, even without knowing their nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when they do come across the sūtras and the dhamma, they need very little instruction, because they've already set everything up correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like the famous story of Pākhir.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was just doing things on his own, wearing the tree bark as his robe, and he thought he was an arahant and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when he met the Buddha, he just gave him a line of instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: In sin, there will be only sin inherited, and he was an arahant right there and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: And people are like, wow, that was a powerful instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the only reason why that instruction worked is because he, although he was wearing a tree bark and doing his own thing, he was actually doing it pretty much rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was authentic to the point of he just needed the one sentence from the Buddha to just slightly tweak whatever understanding he had and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Buddha meant when he said, some people have little dust in their eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, his previous teachers, upon his arahantship, upon his enlightenment, he wanted to go and...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, who should I teach first then?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, I'll teach my previous teacher with very little.
[SPEAKER_00]: He reached the base of neither perception nor perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he has very little dust in his eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just give him a sentence or two and it'll be enough for his full enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because actually, reaching the state of neither perception nor perception in your contemplation, your understanding, your establishment of mind, is quite a tall order.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you can do that, as I said, even a sentence from the suttas will be more than sufficient for arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if you keep that in your mind, in regard to any experience you go through, be it physical or mental, you will
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind will eventually, well, start experiencing disenchantment with those things, because you're just always seeking permanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, without the external instruction, without the external pointer of the suttas, you can't direct that to your self-view, but you can undo pretty much everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when it comes down to undoing your self-view, it won't be that hard.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because self-view is maintained to all of the other wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's maintained through the wrong view of itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no, you can't abandon self-view and still hold other views.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, abandoning self-view means you technically undermine all of the other wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might still be engaging in sensuality and so on, unless you're an anāgāmī, but the nature of it has been seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just need to develop your mind to the extent necessary that that nature of sensuality doesn't pull you any longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not completely, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The the 100% authentic person is is arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means there is no trace of a visual act in any shape, or form, or degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: But exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sotāpanna, sakadāgāmī, anāgāmī, they all have corresponding degrees of bad faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're still not quite looking at certain things.
[SPEAKER_00]: They lack certain things.
[SPEAKER_01]: The ultimate of all things they do, well seems, you know, arranged,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, knowing your motives... Well, first of all, keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not doing anything unwholesome by body, by speech, or by mind, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, especially, you start by not doing anything unwholesome by body, because, no matter how hard you think, oh yeah, I'm being authentic, you're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the domain of a physical action is undermining you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not, you're not, you're not restraining it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just simply needs to be restrained, full stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but no, but no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It needs to be restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, afterwards, it becomes apparent why.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why sīla comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not negotiable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that would be the first step.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once the sīla is in place, then you would start becoming more aware, more mindful of your intentions, of your motivation, why to do this, why to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly how you distinguish whether it's wholesome or it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were about to do something, why am I about to do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I want to do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's my motivation behind it?
[SPEAKER_00]: As I spoke before, sometimes what's externally... what externally appears as wholesome and great and approved by everybody else, actually can be done for unwholesome reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that doesn't mean, like, for example, like, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ideally, you don't want to want anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just want to give.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you still do want, it doesn't mean you should stop making merit, because it still counts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, and also, if you catch yourself wanting a better rebirth, and that's why you give merit, and then you stop giving merit altogether, well, that's like overshooting the mark as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's wrong too.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you want to do is be aware of your motivation, and then change it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't... that's when you stop thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you just have to fully acknowledge the fact that there is a desire for a better rebirth in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by fully acknowledging it, by being fully mindful of it, you'll end up... well, you'll stop acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because only when you're not mindful of things that are in the background, as like a more general intention that's motivating you, then you're being controlled by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, when people sometimes, they kind of know why they're doing something, but they refuse to acknowledge to themselves, and then somebody points it out, and he kind of stops them in their shoes, like, oh, yeah, it's obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, that's an act of bad faith, and that's what you don't want to entertain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you always keep reviewing your mind as to why am I doing this, why am I doing that, why am I saying this, why do I want to do this, why am I about to say that?
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you see something unwholesome, it doesn't mean, okay, I'll stop doing everything now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because that's another act.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, now, you're doing out of fear of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: But acting out of fear is also unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you end up revolving around, you know, panic or whatever else, confusion, doubt, which is all unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you actually, no, you stop and review it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, I want to make merit because I want to be reborn in heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: Making merit counts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just reflect upon the entire situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Making merit counts, no matter what I want or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, that merit will be greater if I don't act out of two selfish reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, you still value, basically, you still recognize that the act of making merit is valid, whether you're selfish or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you don't deny it entirely.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, what you try to do is, while making merit or whatever else, just focus on different aspects, because there are other intentions present.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, like, yeah, you want... the primary intention is you want to be reborn in heaven, but also you want to help to whatever you're given.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or simply, you know that, well, okay, I can't stop wishing to be reborn in heaven, but what I can do is reflect on the nature of the heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also see that that's something impermanent that will not last forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you experience disenchantment in regard to that which you cannot stop wishing for.
[SPEAKER_00]: And automatically, exactly, the pull of your desire towards it stops.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still a fact that if you give, you will be reborn in heaven eventually as a result of the greatness of your gifts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it was nothing to do with you from the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just aspects you were focusing on and you're craving taking over.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you reflect that even that is impermanent, you'll stop craving it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might still want it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a sense, it's factual.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will happen as one of the outcomes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's the problem that people, when they kind of experience... well, it feels like action paralysis.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you get caught up, like, oh, you see you're about to do something unwholesome, or something that comes from the unwholesome reason, but it's not necessarily unwholesome, but then you just stop doing everything, you just stop, shut it down, shut... no, nothing, nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm saying no to everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't possibly sustain it, because, as I said, that's an act that comes out of that unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you actually have to be able to allow it to arise, and then recognize where it comes from, and affect that, not just
[SPEAKER_00]: Throw the baby with the water and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you uproot the desire as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any desire for that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you desire something, well, then you reflect on what you're desiring, on the final goal, final outcome of that desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: You reflect on that long enough, as impermanent, as something that inherently cannot provide satisfaction, and automatically, you... your desire fades.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you directly start to try to tackle your desire, I'm not wishing it, you just end up winding yourself up, more and more, like a dog running, tied to a post, running around it, and just making the... making the leash shorter and shorter and shorter.
[SPEAKER_01]: A suit of...
[SPEAKER_01]: One's that are dear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: One's that are dear, you know, clean, the same being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, the dear ones, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: The dear ones, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about a non-same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having family and so on helps you to see that they are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what I just said in terms of the desire, and what you're just saying in terms of the impermanent, yeah, that's basically... that's the difference between thinking the world is the problem and recognizing that actually the problem is your attitude of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because by default, you don't see your craving, you immediately project, you think the world is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ah, the dear ones are cause for suffering, my family is cause for my pain, friends are cause for suffering, attachment is a cause of pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Deny, deny, deny.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will run away, I will abandon everybody, I will not talk to anybody ever again, because attachment is the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you project it onto the world, and you think that by running away, you will abandon the attachment, but you won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because attachment is actually your attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you stay in the world, or relatively stay in the world, you will not run away or whatever else, or project out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, exactly, by reflecting upon the impermanence, upon the like inherent dissolution of it, eventually, you will experience disenchantment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the abandoning of attachment, not running away.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, you know, you can have arahants living in the middle of a village.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha did.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, well, let the monks who want to live in caves, live in caves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let those who want to live in the cities, live in the cities, for as long as it brings them arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the famous sutra that I often actually quote, the bait, the simile of the bait, when people unbearably eat the bait, eat the food, and Mara lays out for them the deer herd, and then they...
[SPEAKER_00]: Mahārāja does whatever he wants.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then other people see that, other herd sees that, and then they shun the bait completely, run off in the mountains, say no to everything, but they can't sustain that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then they come back, and then they have no choice but to eat unworthily, and then again Mahārāja takes control over them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the third deer herd is the one that sees this bird and says, well, what if we stay in the domain of the bait, but eat it carefully?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then Mahārāja can't see them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're right there, but they're not catching on to the bait, because he can see only those who grab the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're right in the mara's domain, but he can't see you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's often in the suttas, and the Buddha says, the evil one, the unworthy one, can't see me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm invisible to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Next, to see that...
[SPEAKER_01]: I really like the verse.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the...
[SPEAKER_01]: He's telling this woman to reflect.
[SPEAKER_01]: What he's telling this Kuni to reflect.
[SPEAKER_01]: She lost her son.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: He came without your permission.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I thought that was fair.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is there to do for...
[SPEAKER_01]: He came from somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was leaving another way.
[SPEAKER_01]: This way or that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it went without permission.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it becomes utterly pointless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, you can keep the civil
[SPEAKER_00]: The relationship normalizes itself, but internally... And again, it's different than just saying, no, I'm refusing to have contact with them, and things like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there would be... Well, that means you're still attached to it, now you're just denying the whole thing, because you can't free yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like that... unaware group of... that they had... that saw people being controlled on account of the bait, then they shunned the bait, and they ran away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then they came back, because they had no choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you internally experience disenchantment in regard to it, externally, you could be very much in the middle of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, there are things that externally you cannot do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you cannot break the eight precepts, so to speak, intentionally, and around.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot intentionally kill, intentionally engage in sexual intercourse, intentionally steal or lie or things like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the certain awholesome things and the external manifestations of them are entirely gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: But everything else, like... which is why often arahants are not being recognized externally by others, including other arahants sometimes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, see, this is the toughest one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's fundamentally speaking, but whether he wants it or not, makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: But once you experience this enchantment,
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, like, you won't have a problem talking about it, because it's not... it ceases to be like talking about myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Externally, again, people can think, oh, he's full of himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the first thing the Buddha said upon his enlightenment, when he was walking on the road, when that man met him and says, oh, your senses are clear and bright, you look
[SPEAKER_00]: Peaceful, uh, whose teaching did you follow to reach that peace and clarity?
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said, I don't follow anyone, Steve.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm my own leader.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm my own teacher.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've enlightened myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm the greatest in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this man says, right, so be it, friend, and walks off.
[SPEAKER_00]: He thought, like, good God, he's just full of himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not gonna talk to him, and left him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha was not wrong in saying any of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he's the greatest in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, if you say that to putujana, to somebody who is not free from the self-view, they cannot possibly not take it in a conceited sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why, you know, when Sister Vajira, in the letters, only later realized the true meaning of anathimāni, non-conceit, because she thought Jñānavīra was full of himself, and she really had a go at him, trying to really challenge him.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when she failed, and then come to see the reason, and get right with him, she realized, no, actually, he was truly humble.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, you read that externally, you couldn't tell, if you wouldn't know, if you wouldn't yourself have a reference point for what the real humility means.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, the other Sutta, when the Buddha... when that woman was... we spoke about it the other day, when she was saying to Nanda, oh, how come my uncle and my father, although they were the same, they were reborn in different heavens, and so on, and the Buddha said, because of different faculties, and then he goes on saying,
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes, a person can externally be pleasing to everybody, to monks, to lay people, just the greatest person, the humblest, the meekest and everything, but he holds on to the wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, basically, externally, whatever he is, it's utterly irrelevant, because the wrong views will take him down, not bring him to the better rebirth in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, constantly, like, opposite of that, you're a person who is prone to anger, prone to being irritated, prone to lust, prone to aversion, externally, you know, people think he's a bit of a, you know, a prick, and... but he has right views.
[SPEAKER_00]: He did develop right views.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, he will go up afterwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's far from ideal, but he's still...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the external is not the measure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can be an indicator, but it's far from being a measure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, fewness of the wishes and so on, that's an internal attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, depending on the person's faculties, are bringing... and, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: Depending on previous lives and habits that have been cultivated, like neutral habits that have been cultivated for so long, they might be speaking like a really, really arrogant whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know it all.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm full of myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although, they might be an arahant, or on the way to become one.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where Putujan's authenticity comes in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you shouldn't...
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, it's how you should... you should not... you should not...
[SPEAKER_00]: Criticize anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should accept everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, every view you should accept.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every view is the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... that's nonsense.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you do need to distinguish between right and wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're authentic, you'll know, okay, this makes more sense, or this doesn't make so much sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't fully dismiss, nor do you fully commit, in a sense, you don't forget that you're still a putrugena.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you follow the one that makes more sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you keep reflecting upon it and re-evaluating it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because you clearly keep in your mind that you're still a patujana, you never fully shut the door to things being different.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if sometime down the line, you now find out that this view was utterly wrong, you won't have a problem dropping it in an instant and finding a better one, the one that makes more sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're inauthentic though, you will have a big problem out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why, you know, you get 40-50 Vāsāyājans, and if their view gets challenged, it's just the entire existence is being kind of trembling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they shut the doors very early, and went down the wrong lane, too far to be able to come back.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not optional anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what you don't want to happen to you, or to anybody else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to be authentic, and then, exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when you think you're right, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: Test it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I told you before... Oh, wow!
[SPEAKER_00]: As I've told you before, like... when I started reading philosophy and dhamma and the suttas, the... being in nothingness made quite a big impact on me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was quite insightful and...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, like a revelation.
[SPEAKER_00]: I read it, I think, six or seven times.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then I found Yanavera, started reading Yanavera.
[SPEAKER_00]: That made even more sense, because it was like existential philosophy attitude about the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was exactly like, oh, the missing link, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I really got into that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, found Yanavera was a lot influenced by Sartre, and his writing, and even his way of writing was similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is great for me, because I was already very familiar with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then he kept saying, well, it's like, in reference to this or that, how sātra is wrong here, sātra is wrong there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I couldn't see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I couldn't see how sātra was wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for me, like, I could have deluded myself and said, well, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I saw what sātra meant, and I thought I was right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, Nyanavidā says what sātra meant here is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I could have deluded myself and said, well, Nyanavira is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't know what he's talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's following himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I was too afraid to abandon my views.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I wasn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then I kept reading Nyanavira.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then I was becoming afraid to read Being and Nothingness, or to find any reference to Sātre, because in my mind, I felt like I'm gaining understanding of what Nyanavira is saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if I were to go back and read Sātre's work,
[SPEAKER_00]: And if I would still feel him right, there would be a contradiction in terms, because I can't have both, Yanavera right and Sārcha right, because Yanavera said Sārcha is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I fully understand both, I'll see how Yanavera is right, and I'll see how Sārcha was wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: And lots of people are actually afraid to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're afraid to undermine their own views, which means they're afraid to upgrade them, because upgrade is a form of a change.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they're afraid to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for a while, I was afraid, but I kept going with Nyanavira, but I couldn't, you know, I wouldn't open anything of Sārcā.
[SPEAKER_00]: I had the whole 12-stack collection my mother brought me from Serbia, that I bought ages ago, all of his works.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, I remember, once I was like, well, you know, it's not postponing, I really have to see where I'm at.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I opened the Transcendence of Ego, his kind of shorter work, which I remember it was so... quite a revelation for me to read the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was like so, like, wow, accurate, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I was afraid I won't see his wrong views there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fortunately enough, like, first, second paragraph, it became, oh,
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, yeah, I did actually understand in the Veda, at that point, sufficiently enough to see how such was wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which was clearly a measure of progress for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then I just kept going.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that also means that you cease to be afraid from any challenge of any other view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then I will go to library and pick up... Well, I would pick up knowingly stuff that are wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like all the nonsense they have in the West, in the libraries, all the new age
[SPEAKER_00]: Books and then, you know, the acid head gurus from India or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wouldn't bother with that because it's just too plainly wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then the stuff that was kind of borderline, I would get that and read it and try to see it's not just, oh, this is wrong because I don't like him and I know what he got up to or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: I had to read the views, I had to understand the views, and I had to see how and where they were wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I had a similar thing when I was reading Samana Pāla Sutta, the fruits of the ascetic life in Dīgha Nikaya, when the Buddha lists the six main kind of bases for the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when people think there's nobody killed, and you can go and just chop everybody's head off along the east side of Ganges, and this side of Ganges, and nobody ever dies, it's just elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: First time I read that, to me, felt every of those views felt right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, there is no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no good in reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is...
[SPEAKER_00]: I was a layman back then, 18, 19 years old.
[SPEAKER_01]: By chance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then as I'm reading, I thought the Buddha is just listing these great views.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then he says, all these views are wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I was, oh my goodness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I just thought they're all right.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't see how they're wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, I could have just done a blind eye to it, or I could have made the effort and see exactly why they're wrong, which is what I've done.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what he... like, when he talks, you should interrogate, investigate, re-evaluate.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like, you know, sitting and staring at the floor or nodding your head down and watching your breath until you fall asleep.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Be like full-on active.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if you're into samādhi, if you're a samādhi type, when people often used to disregard, not making, like, to justify not making the effort to understand the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm a samādhi type.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, only if you're an arahant, you can say whether you're a samādhi type or vipassana type.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not before that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if you go to sit and meditate, you should be developing the right views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That constant drilling, uprooting, abandoning, upgrading, whatever else, whatever it takes,
[SPEAKER_00]: Until you... until your very knowledge, not a chance, not a circumstance, nothing given externally to you that can be taken, until something that you fully developed and you fully understood by yourself is the result, is the cause of you being free from suffering and free from possibility to suffer ever again in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the practice is and that's where it should end.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where it should lead.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you need to have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Read the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Nibiru is such an important book, because it was that... it was that, like, necessary starting point, just telling you how to start.
[SPEAKER_00]: I often say to people, well, even if you don't get anything more from clearing the path, at least if you get the attitude that you should have towards the suttas, that's a good starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, like, yeah, you can help people,
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely disregarding certain parts of the suttas, they're contradicting their views, yet at the same time think they're practicing the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to understand something from the suttas, you'd be at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, if you're not a sotāpanna, there is no understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no grey area there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was... like, it's just such an obvious thing, but even I needed to hear it from the Nabiru.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just doesn't occur to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Especially because all the contemporary stuff that's out there, that it's telling you otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I'm not reading, because the Nabiru keeps saying that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when we saw the Qur'an, I was like... and I think... and then you look at the suttas and you realize, yeah, it says that, but you just never pay attention to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: On many occasions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's continue.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you cross over things, you don't pay attention to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They stand out more than I do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, let's... let's be... it became apparent to me in early days, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I was doing lots of walking meditation and contemplating things, and I realized, well, hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am contemplating the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what makes me think that the tools that are used for contemplation, basic concepts that are used for contemplation, what makes me think that that's right?
[SPEAKER_00]: How do I know that?
[SPEAKER_00]: You just assume that the tools that were given to you were right, and then you just start working with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: What if they're not right?
[SPEAKER_00]: It means the outcome that you make with those tools will never be right either.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the tools I'm referring to are these basic concepts such as consciousness, perception, feeling, intentionality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it became apparent to me that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Your definitions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: What I, in twenty-something years, what I have developed, what I've kind of gathered,
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness, to me, well, I'm a puthujjana, which means my understanding of what consciousness is, is puthujjana, which means there is no understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was in the early days, and I realized that, okay, so actually it's not about finding, it's just undoing stuff that you already have, because what you have, you got it wrongly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then I switched and started doing my walking meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was in Harlem, in a little room.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it was just maybe four or five steps.
[SPEAKER_00]: One way, the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: One way, diagonally.
[SPEAKER_00]: From wall to wall.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it was enough to keep me going.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I kept doing it there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, I just...
[SPEAKER_00]: I would literally just take up...
[SPEAKER_00]: I was still on the Garika.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take up consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And just keep thinking what consciousness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I don't mean referring to, you know, some...
[SPEAKER_00]: ...psychological descriptions, nonsense, whatever else, but just generally, okay, if I say consciousness out loud, right now, what does that stand for, right now, in my experience?
[SPEAKER_00]: It needs to stand for something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you couldn't be able to even say it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can do that in regard to everything, but you want to bring it down to the most general, most fundamental terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: The five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Matter, feeling, perception, intentionality, and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you start thinking like that, and you realize it's not about building things, just... not even bothering with the tools, just undoing that which I thought are tools, because all of that was taken for granted, and that was already the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you undo that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all you have to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that you have to undo the wrong tools and then build the right thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Undoing that means building the right thing.